[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
in 2020 a fake study was published on
the gluteus maximus basically looking at
squats versus hip thrusts now it's this
Infamous barbolo study barbalo was a
student under Paula genteel and it
looked at the effects of squats versus
hip thrusts and it was fake as a
practitioner everyone knew it was fake
you know people who trainers and coaches
who prescribe squats and hip thrusts the
data did not line up with real world
results but the statisticians took a
look at it and hammered it and since
then for this group's papers have been
retracted and now people realize that
the study never took place well back
when that happened I was talking to my
colleague meno hanselmans we said we
really do need a study on squads and
hypnosis and ideally it would use MRI
but MRI is expensive so a few years
later meno calls me up hey Brett let's
do this let's get that study conducted
coincidentally I'd been talking to Mike
Roberts
um who's a very well respected scientist
and he's like hey I got this student
Daniel Plotkin now Daniel studied under
Mike Israel and Brad schoenfeld he's an
awesome student he said Daniel can get
it done let's do this well MRIs are
expensive so meno and I each contributed
40 Grand to get this experiment
conducted and we finally posted about it
on June 24th now the title of the paper
is hip thrust and back squat training
elicit similar gluteal muscle
hypertrophy and transfers similarly to
the deadlift so here's what happened
it's a nine week long study now the
subjects were all beginners new to
strength training they were aged 20 to
28 we looked at men and women there
ended up being 18 participants in the
hypnos group five men and 13 women and
16 participants in the squat group six
men and 10 women the training regimen
was nine weeks long and it was
periodized like this for week one the
subjects did three sets of either squats
or hip thrusts twice a week week two was
four sets per session so eight total
sets for the week now weeks three
through six the subjects did five sets
per session and weeks seven through nine
they did six sets per session so
basically 12 weekly sets of either
squads or hip thrusts so they start off
with three sets ended with six sets per
session obviously Progressive overload
was utilized hip dress were with a
barbell you know standard barbell hip
dust squats were mostly High bar and the
sub just went as deep as possible
without screwing up their form so I
think most of the subjects went below
parallel so out of the 16 squat subjects
one of them was super tall and he
couldn't get that deep interestingly his
glutes grew just fine his glutes grew
very well two to three of the subjects
were a little bit above parallel and the
remaining 12 or 13 were at least a
parallel or well below parallel now this
is a really cool paper because we looked
at a lot of things we looked at EMG you
know electromyography to look at was it
predictive of glue hypertrophy you know
hip thrust led to a lot greater
gluteactive then squats did but it did
lead to more growth so that was the
first main finding was that EMG did not
predict hypertrophy because squats get a
better stretch and muscle produces Force
actively and passively so the squat
probably has more passive Force
production the hip to us more active
Force production leading to a tie in
muscle growth we also looked at
hypertrophy using MRI the gold standard
and we looked at a lot of different
muscles and muscle areas so the first
was a gluteus maximus but we looked at
the very lower glute Max the mid and the
upper okay we looked at glute medius and
Minimus combined we looked at the
adductors the quadriceps and the
hamstrings now I'm going to put a giant
chart up here so you can kind of watch
it as I announce the results for upper
glute Max hip thrust led to a 13.7
percent Improvement squats 12.8 percent
for the mid glute Max hip dust 10.7
percent squats 10.1 percent and then
lower glute Max hip thrust 21.5 percent
squats 19.2 percent so very similar
gluteus maximus muscle growth for the
glute medius and Minimus hip thrust led
to 3.2 percent change squats 0.8 percent
so neither group glue the group medius
that well for the quadriceps hip thrust
6.8 percent improvements squats 12.6 so
almost double the quadricep growth with
squats adductors 4.1 percent with the
hip thrust 10.3 percent with squats so
over two and a half times more adductor
growth with squats and finally
hamstrings point eight percent growth
with hip thrust and 1.6 percent with
squats so interestingly neither group
grew the hamstrings that well either now
we also looked at strength transfer now
obviously due to the rule of specificity
squats are going to build squat strength
more than hip thrust and hip thrusts are
going to build hypto strength more than
squats that's like the most basic law of
strength training is the law of
specificity but what about deadlifts and
horizontal wall pushing basically the
wall pushes how hard you can push
horizontally into wall so this would
kind of measure how hard you can push
forward which is important Sports in
everyday life so when you take two
non-specific exercises what led to
better results well so let's look at the
chart in the three rep max squat the hip
thrust gained 16.7 percent and the squad
group gained 43.1 percent so squats way
more effective for squat strength for
the hip thrust 3 rep max the hip thrust
group went up 65.1 percent and the squat
group went up 33.4 percent now here's
what's interesting so with the deadlift
3 rep max there was a perfect tie both
squats and hip thrusts both increased
15.3 percent so they led to the exact
same deadlift strength gains and for the
wall push it was a 10 increase for the
hip thrust group and a 7.7 percent
increase for the squat group put another
way the hip dos group put 19.1 pounds on
their squat
116.2 pounds on their hip thrust 20.3
pounds on their deadlift and 6.7 pounds
on their wall push the squat group to
put 48.7 pounds on their squat 59.3
pounds on their hip thrust 20.3 pounds
on their deadlift and 5.1 pounds on
their wall push so let's discuss these
results most people felt hip thrust
working their glutes more but there was
equal growth and subjects probably felt
sore with squats but it led to equal
growth so where you feel it so so
sensation doesn't always equal muscle
growth soreness feeling the muscle dose
don't always predict hypertrophy EMG
didn't predict hypertrophy I thought
that it would I was wrong I thought that
the lower glute Max would have similar
gains but middle and upper glute Max
gains would be optimized with hip thrust
and that wasn't the case they led to the
same glute growth in all three the upper
mid and lower on all three segments so
you tend to feel hip thrust working more
of the upper area and you tend to feel
squats working more the lower but that
was not reflective with hypertrophy now
gluteus medius activation is pretty high
high with hip thrust but it didn't lead
to much growth so this indicates that
you would want to do frontal plane
abduction to maximize glute medius
growth if you're looking to grow the
upper glutes of the Shelf you've got to
throw an abduction hamstring EMG is
pretty high during hip thrusts but it
didn't grow the hamstrings either during
squats it makes sense then the hammies
wouldn't grow much because you don't get
much muscle length change plus you're
trying to extend the knees not Flex them
but I did think hip thrust would grow
the hammies and they didn't and it makes
sense that quad growth would be higher
with squats you move through more knee
range of motion and same with adductor
growth because you go deeper and the
adductors are huge hip extensors at the
bottom of a squat it was interesting
with strength gains I did think that the
hip dust would lead to Greater wall push
strength because that hip angle is more
similar to hip thrust but that wasn't
the case and with deadlifts I did
predict that I thought they'd be similar
now I suspect that squads lead to better
strength gains off the floor for the
deadlift and hip thrust lead to better
lockout strength so cloth Inhibitors are
both decent deadlift assistance
exercises now we didn't have a combined
group that would have been forty
thousand more bucks but it would have
been great because we could have seen
our squads and hip thrusts synergistic
meaning is there an additive effect or
is it redundant if you did get better
results with the combined group then
that would suggest that hip thrusts lead
to muscle growth through more active
mechanisms and squash through more
passive mechanisms thereby lending
support to what bodybuilders do which is
training muscles at a variety of muscle
Lanes now it could be that the hip
thrust shouldn't be thought of as a
short position movement because you do
go pretty deep in a hip thrust not as
deep as a squat but maybe you go deep
enough in a hip thrust or like I said
earlier maybe hip thrusts generate more
active force and squats more passive
Force we still need to learn why I do
think this subject design favored the
squat interestingly some experts said
well squats are require more
coordination so you're not going to get
a lot of growth with squats up front
because they're going to be you know
uncoordinated and not well balanced but
I don't think that's the case I think
that doing two days a week favors the
squat because you know especially
beginners they could hit thrust five
days a week you don't get real sore from
hip thrust you can recover quickly they
don't lead as much fatigue so you could
hip to us five days a week as a beginner
whereas squats beat you up a little bit
more two days a week is probably optimal
for squatting but not for hip thrusting
but every study has pros and cons you
know every study has limitations and it
can only be applied to that particular
study design so what this study did show
was beginners training their glutes
twice a week saw similar results
regardless of whether they perform
squats or hip thrusts what would happen
with Advanced subjects what would happen
with a combined group what would happen
with different volumes and frequencies
we can only speculate so this paper has
been talked about a lot on social media
the squat only and like the power
lifting camps they get to Safe face
because they get to to say see I told
you don't even waste your time with hip
just just Squat and you get big glutes
and you also get big quads and big
adductors and big legs and you get more
squat gains and the same deadlift gains
and the bikini competitors in the hip
thrust only camps they get to say phase
two they get to say C don't waste your
time with squats just do hip thrusts you
just grow your glutes you don't you know
we don't want big legs we don't want
quads and adductors we want mostly
glutes and it doesn't beat you up as
much it's easier it's safer you know
they can also say hey in the real world
you know to get a study published you
have to equate the volume in the real
world we don't have to equate the volume
we can do way more sets of hip thrust
than we can squats so clearly hippos are
superior but any logical person would
come to the conclusion that you should
probably do both not only for maximizing
functional strength but also for
maximizing glute muscle size glute
hypertrophy and leg hypertrophy tooth so
just remember every study is a puzzle
piece and it it just provides some clues
some evidence but you know when you have
an entire puzzle put together each piece
is critical each piece is important but
we need a lot more research we need way
more hip thrust studies way more glute
studies in general to really be sure of
how to grow the glutes the best in the
meantime you should definitely do both
squats and hip thrusts if they feel good
for you most people can find variations
of hip thrust variations of squats that
feel good for their bodies but let's say
squats didn't feel good for you you
could probably find a single leg
movement that felt good like a Bulgarian
split squat or a step up or a type of
lunge you might not like barbell hippos
but maybe the glute drive or the Smith
machine feels good for you nevertheless
I thought you'd like a recap of this
study it'll be the first of a long line
of glute research that I intend on
funding in the next video I post it's
going to be about the whole muscle
length debate pertaining to the glutes
and what experiments we need to conduct
to really get a good idea of how to best
train the glutes thank you very much for
watching please make sure you hit like
if you like the video please make sure
you subscribed to my channel and
definitely leave a comment let me know
what you think about this study let me
know how you interpret the results I
always like reading what you guys have
to say thanks again for watching